Finding Aid for Irene Linda Lather Butler papers, 1923-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Irene Linda Lather Butler papers 1923-1991
Butler, Irene Linda Lather, 1901-1991.
3 linear feet
93800 Aa 2
Registered nurse and artist from Grand Rapids, Michigan and Tucson, Arizona. Letters exchanged with William Butler during their courtship and the first months of their marriage, 1923-1925; diaries, 1915-1979, detailing daily life and observations; subject files relating in part to her interest in nursing and sculpture.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 1992 by the estate of Irene Butler (donor no. 7602 ) and through the assistance of her niece, Nancy D. Cook.
The collection is open to research.
Irene Linda Lather Butler was born on July 8, 1901 in Traverse City, Michigan. Active in many areas, she was both a registered nurse and an artist of some fame. After completing high school, Irene Lather in September 1919 completed a three-year course of study at the Blodgett School of Nursing at Blodgett Hospital in Grand Rapids, Michigan. She continued her education, completing a specialized course in obstetrics on June 20, 1923 at Dr. Joseph B Delee's Lying-In-Hospital. After this four-month course, she received a diploma and a gold pin with a diamond, certifying that she had completed the course and could deliver babies if necessary.
Irene Linda Lather married William Butler on March 15, 1924 in Kalamazoo, Michigan. When her husband became the head of the Department of Urology at the Grand Rapids Clinic in 1925, Irene Butler worked for him as his nurse and secretary. In 1931 she joined the Women's Auxiliary to the Kent County Medical Society. She was appointed membership chairman for 1935-36 and was elected president in 1938. Also active in the Michigan State Medical Society, she was elected exhibition chairman in 1938 and in 1939 she was elected treasurer and in 1941 president.
Irene Butler was also an artist whose work has been exhibited in various prominent galleries in Grand Rapids and Arizona. In 1933, she first began studying painting and sculpture at the Grand Rapids Art Gallery. In 1956 she was honored with a one-person show of her work at the Gallery. Wood and stone sculptures of hers were displayed, as well as paintings. When she and her husband retired to Tucson, Arizona, she devoted her time to artistic endeavors. Irene Linda Lather Butler died December 23, 1991 at the age of 90.
The Irene Butler collection consists of four series of papers: Personal/Biographical, Correspondence, Diaries, and Artistic Endeavors. Together these series reflect Butler's lively mind and her awareness of the world about her.
Subjects:
Artists--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Butler, Irene Linda Lather.; Courtship.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Love letters.; Nurses--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Nursing--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Women artists--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Sculptors--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Women sculptors--Michigan--Grand Rapids.
Contributors:
Butler, William.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Personal/Biographical
  The Personal/Biographical series (0.25 linear foot) consists of photocopies of photographs of Irene as she grew up and became a nurse. There are also photocopies of images of her family taken near the turn of the century. Also included is an undated term paper Irene wrote while in training to become a nurse. Irene Butler's autobiography - Live, Live, Live is also available at the Bentley Historical Library.
  - Photocopies of photographs of Irene Butler and her family, including photocopies from the period of her childhood and when she was studying to be a nurse, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - School term paper relating to history of nursing, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (0.75 linear feet) consists of correspondence exchanged with her husband-to-be. The majority of the letters were written between 1923 and 1925 during their engagement and the first months of their marriage. Another group of letters document her organizational activities with the Michigan State Medical Society Auxiliary and the Grand Rapids League of Women Voters.
  - Personal
    - Letters from Irene Butler to William Butler, October 29, 1923-October 29, 1979 (mainly 1923-1925), 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Letters from William Butler to Irene Butler, June 30, 1923-March 15, 1981 (mainly 1923-1925), 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Undated letters exchanged between Irene and William (Box 1)
    - Letter to a friend relating to her nursing career, 1920s (Box 1)
  - Organizational
    - Michigan State Medical Society Auxiliary, 1942-1972 (Box 1)
    - Various associations (including: Grand Rapids League of Women Voters, American Red Cross, art associations), 1942-1952 (Box 1)
- Diaries
  The Diaries series (1915-1979; 1.25 linear feet) is a record of Irene Butler's life's activities beginning in 1915 when she was fifteen and ending when she was 78 years old. The travel diaries describe events that occurred while she was vacationing throughout the U.S. over the years and once to Europe in 1961. Her "Sunday only" diaries, which she began writing when she was 86, consist of more detailed, personal reflections written near the end of her life.
  - 1915-1979, 49 volumes (Box 2)
  - Travel diaries (includes trips throughout U.S. as well as a trip to Europe in 1961) 1939-1985, 22 volumes (Box 3)
  - Sundays only diaries, 1987-1989, 6 volumes (Box 3)
- Artistic Activities
  The Artistic Activities series (0.25 linear feet) consists of art exhibit brochures, many from exhibits in Arizona where she had her work displayed. There are also photocopies of many works of art she had created throughout her life.
  - Art Exhibit Brochures, mainly from Arizona (Box 3)
  - Photocopies of her art work (Box 3)